<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of within the dioces of London, in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in God, Ihon Bishop of London, 1589 in the xxxj. yeare of the raigne of Our Most Gratious Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1577-1594 : Aylmer)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10252.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22914631</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22914631</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25870</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00204)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25870)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1777:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of within the dioces of London, in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in God, Ihon Bishop of London, 1589 in the xxxj. yeare of the raigne of Our Most Gratious Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of London. Bishop (1577-1594 : Aylmer)</author>
                  <author>Aylmer, John, 1521-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[T. Orwin],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Name of publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped at bottom with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Magdalene College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25870:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25870:1"/>
            <p>❀ ARTICLES, TO BE ENQVIRED OF within the Dioces of London, in <hi>the viſitation of the Reuerend Father</hi> in God, <hi>Ihon</hi> Biſhop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. <hi>1589.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the xxxj. yeare of the raigne of our <hi>moſt gratious ſoueraigne Lady ELIZABETH</hi> by the grace of GOD Queene of England, <hi>Fraunce, and Ireland, defender</hi> of the faith. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London, 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath_for_church_wardens">
            <pb facs="tcp:25870:2"/>
            <head>The tenor of the othe miniſtred to the Church-wardens and ſworn-men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ee ſhall ſweare that all affection, fauour, hatred, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or malice ſet a ſide, you ſhall vpon due conſideration of the Articles ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you in charge, preſent all and euery ſuch perſon of or within your pariſh, as hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted any offence or fault, or made any default mentioned in theſe or any of theſe Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected, or otherwiſe defamed of any ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, fault, or default: wherein you ſhal deale vprightly and according to equitie, neither of malice preſenting any contrarie to truth, nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent anie, and ſo conceale the truth; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine truth, and to ſuppreſſe vice. So helpe you God, and his faithfull promiſes contained in theſe his holie bookes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charge_of_church_wardens">
            <head>The charge of the Church-wardens and ſworne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſet downe for the better performance of their duties, and diſcharge of their oathes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey are ſtraightly charged to heare all theſe articles read ouer vnto them, and diligently to conſider and enquire thereof. And for that the time is ſo ſhort in this the viſitation, that they ſhall not be able to make a perfect anſwere vnto all of them, and that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there are manie notorious faultes preſently worthy of preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reformation: they are charged to make their anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them preſently, ſo farre forth as their memory ſhall now ſerue them: And to preſent now ſuch faultes in their Pariſh, as at this time are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of preſentment and reformation. And that after their comming home betwixt this and Michaelmas next, they ſhall agayne heare all the Articles read ouer vnto them, and diligently conſider and enquire thereof with the Miniſter of the Pariſh, who ſhall (if he know any thing in the Pariſh to be reformed) together with them make a due preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a true and full aunſwere in wryting, ſigned with their handes and markes, wherein they ſhall preſent aſwell all ſuch faultes or offences, contrarie to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as they forgot or omitted to preſent at the time of the viſitation, as alſo all ſuch faultes and offences contrarie to the Articles as ſhall happen and chaunce betwixt this and then.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:25870:2"/>
            <head>¶Articles to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of within the Dioces of London <hi>in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation, holden in the yeare</hi> of our Lord God. 1589.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Articles concerning the Cleargie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether Common praier bée read by your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in your ſeuerall Churches or Chappels di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and reuerently, and in ſuch order as it is ſet foorth by the lawes of this Realme, without any kind of alteration omitting or adding to any thing, and at due and conuenient houres, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter wearing a Surples? And whether the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sacraments be likewiſe miniſtred reuerently in ſuch manner, as by the booke of Common praier is appoynted. And whether vpon Wedneſdaies and Fridaies, not being holi-daies, the Letanie and other praiers appoynted for the day be ſayd accordingly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Item, whether the forme of Comination againſt ſinners bée by your Miniſter plainlie and diſtinctly read in your Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vnto the people, according to the Booke.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether any Parſon or Parſons, not being ordered at the leaſt be a Deacon, do ſay Common praier openlie in your Church or Chappell, or do ſolemnize matrimonie, or adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Baptiſme, and what be their names that do ſo?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether the Parſon, Vicar, or Farmer of your Benefice do cauſe or ſuffer any Curate or Miniſter to ſerue your Church before he bee examined and admitted by the Ordinarie in writing, and do ſhewe his licenſe to the Church-wardens.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether your Miniſter doo ſerue two Cures in one daie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he muſt néedes be driuen to ſerue the one of them at inconuenient houſes?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate doo euerie Sonday whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no Sermon, read diſtinctlie and plainlie ſome part of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies preſcribed and ſet foorth by the Quéenes authoritie to be read: and whether any Miniſter not admitted by the Ordinarie, or by other
<pb facs="tcp:25870:3"/>
lawfull authoritie, doe expound anie ſcripture or matter of doctrine, by the waie of exhortation or otherwiſe, and thereby omit and leaue off the reading of the Homilies. Or be there any in your Pariſh that do depraue or ſpeake againſt the Homilies and the vſe of them in the Church?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether any Lectures, Conuenticles, or priuate méetings bée read or vſed within your Pariſhes, either publique in the Church, or priuate in the houſe, by any not ſufficiently licenſed thereunto by the Ordinarie: or whether any ſuch Reader do teach any Doctrine of Innouation to withdrawe the people from due obedience to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Church ſet forth by publique authoritie, or to cauſe them to forbeare participating in praier and Sacraments with our Church?</p>
               <p n="8">8 How many Sermons doth your Parſon or Vicar preach in his owne Church yearely: and if he be no Preacher himſelfe, how many doth he yearely procure to be preached there, and who haue preached them: and whether bee they that do preach them licenſed or no, and by whom were they licenſed?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether your Miniſter haue or do receiue to the holie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion any perſons which be not of his owne Pariſh, without teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie from the Miniſter of the place where they dwell: what they be, that it may appeare that they be not perſons excommunicate?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, do euery Sonday and Holi-day openly in the Church call for, heare, and inſtruct all the children, apprentiſes, and ſeruants of both ſexes, that bee of conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient age within your Pariſh, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe as the time will ſerue, and as he may well heare or inſtruct for one houre at the leaſt, before or after Euening praier in the tenne Commandements, the Articles of the beléefe, and the Lords praier, and diligently examine and teach them the Catechiſme, as it is now allowed and ſet forth in the Booke of Common praier. And whether for that purpoſe he doth take the names of them all, and by courſe call certaine of them euery Sonday and Holi-day to come to the teaching of this Catechiſme?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, Curate, or other Miniſter in your Church or Chappell hath admitted to the holie Communion any open and notorious fornicator, adulterer or euill liuer, by whom publique offence is giuen without due penaunce firſt done, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction of the Congregation enioyned him by his Ordinarie. Or any malicious perſon that is notoriouſly knowne and detected to bée
<pb facs="tcp:25870:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
out of charitie, or detected to haue done any open wrong to his neighbour by word or déede, without due reconciliation firſt made to the partie that is wronged?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether in any of your Pariſhes your Miniſter bee brought in by popular election, ſent by ſome peculier election of miniſterie, confirmed by the Pariſh, and ſo allowed priuatly of before the ſayd Miniſter be preſented to his Ordinarie?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether your Parſon or Vicar haue anie other benefice beſides this: if he ſo haue, where lieth it, how long in the yere is he abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this; how doth he ſée the cure of this ſerued, and what hoſpitality kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth he on this Benefice?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether your Preachers or Miniſter be peace-makers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort their pariſhioners to obedience towards their Prince, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be in authoritie, and to charitie and mutuall loue among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: whether they be diligent in viſiting the ſicke, and in comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether anie doo preach, declare or ſpeak anie thing in deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the booke of Common praier which is ſet forth by the lawes of this Realme, diſpraiſing or deprauing the ſame or anie thing therein contained, or againſt the preachers or miniſters of the word and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments by law authorized?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether your Parſons, Vicars, Curates and Miniſters keep well their Regiſters of all weddings, burials, and chriſtinings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your pariſh according to the Order of the Quéenes Iniunctions, and whether they read the Queeenes Maieſties Iniunctions euerie quarter of a yere once or no?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether they or anie of them kéepe anie ſuſpected woman in their houſes, or be incontinent perſons giuen to drunkennes, idlenes, or be haunters of tauernes, ale-houſes, or ſuſpected places, hunters, hawkers, dicers, carders, common table plaiers, ſwearers, dancers, or otherwiſe ſuſpected of anie notorious crime, or light and vnſéeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie behauior, or giue anie euill example of life, or vſe diſordered and unſeemlie apparell, either in colours, gards, or light faſhion?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether they or any of them do keep or ſuffer to be kept in their parſonage or vicaredge houſes, anie ale-houſes, tippling houſes, or tauernes, or do ſelbale, beere, wine, or anie other victuall?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether for the receiuing of the perambulation of the circuite of your pariſh, the Parſon, Vicar or Curate, Churchwardens, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the ſubſtantiall men of the pariſh in the daies of the Rogaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; daies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> called Gang-daies walke the accuſtomed Boundes
<pb facs="tcp:25870:4"/>
of your pariſh.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Whether anie new Preſbyteries or Elderſhip be latelie among you erected, and by them anie Miniſters appointed without Orders taking of the Biſhops, to baptiſe, miniſter the communion, or deale in anie function eccleſiaſticall or contrarie to law gather anie priuate conuenticle whereby the people be drawne from the Church.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether there be anie in your pariſh that readeth anie priuate lectures in the ſame, or vſeth expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcriptures in any priuate mans houſe whatſoeuer, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the law. And whether anie prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, and dooth not at certaine times in the yeare miniſter the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their owne perſons, and in ſuch Church where he readeth his lecture.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Whether there be anie in your pariſh, Miniſters, or Preachers, that vſe either priuate or other aſſemblies out of their Dioces, with other preachees, or other with them: and doo in them vſe to ſet down anie orders contrary to the orders obſerued in the Queenes Booke, or anie in your pariſh that doo contribute to anie ſuch preachers, and what be the names as well of the contributors, as of them to whom they doo contribute, and what ſeuerall ſummes do they contribute?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether any Miniſter do reiect thoſe women being maried, which doo come to the Church to giue thankes after Child-birth, according to the order ſet downe in the booke of common praier?</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate haue maried anie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not being three ſeueral Sondaies or Feſtiuali daies lawfully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their pariſh Churches, or not being ſufficiently licenſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and by whoſe licenſe the ſame perſons were ſo diſpenſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to be maried?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether anie contention haue growen amongſt the preachers in theſe parts for anie matter of doctrine or ceremonies: and what &amp; who was the cauſe thereof: and whether any ſtrife hath grown about pewes or ſeates in the Church, and betweene whom was it?</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether your Parſons, Vicars or Curates doo keep a iuſt and perfect noſe of all ſuch as doo communicate in their ſeuerall pariſhes, and doo not rather regard their priuate gain, receiuing their offrings at Eaſter, and deliuering them tokens, and ſo enter them into their booke, and certefie as Communicants thoſe who neuer receiued?</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether there be anie Miniſters or Prieſts within your pariſh which liue idlie without anie Cure, neither ſeruing in anie place, nor hauing anie place of reading or preaching?</p>
               <p n="28">28 Whether anie Miniſter doo refuſe to vſe, or neglect ſuch godly
<pb facs="tcp:25870:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
exerciſes of prayer and preaching, as be by publique authoritie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for preſeruation of her Maieſtie, the Countrey, and Church: or for thanks-giuing for any victorie gotten ouer Gods enimies, and the States of the Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Articles concerning the Church.</head>
               <p>WHether haue you in your Pariſh Churches and Chappels all thinges neceſſarie and requiſite for Common praier, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, eſpecially the Booke of Common praier with the newe Kalender, two Pſalters, the Engliſh Bible in the largeſt volume of the edition ſet forth by the Biſhops, and lately imprinted by the Quéenes Printer, the Table of the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, a conuenient Pulpet well placed, a comely and decent Table ſtanding on a frame for the holie Communion, with a fayre linnen cloath to lay vpon the ſame, and ſome couering of ſilke, buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keram, or other ſuch like for the cleane kéeping thereof, a fayre and comely Communion cup of ſiluer, and a couer of ſiluer for the ſame, which may ſerue alſo for the miniſtration of the Communion bread, a decent large Surpleſſe with ſléeues, a ſure Cofer with two lockes and keyes for kéeping of the Regiſter booke, and a ſtrong cheſt or boxe for the almes of the poore, with thrée lockes and keyes to the ſame, and all other things neceſſarie in and to the premiſſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether any do make any layſtals, or vſe to lay any filthineſſe againſt the Church walles, to the anoyance of the Church or of the people, aſſembling themſelues to heare Gods word, and publique exerciſe of praier?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether your Churches and Chappels with the Chauncell be wel and ſufficiently repaired and kept without abuſe of any thing, and whether your Church-yards bee well fenced and cleanly kept, and if any part thereof be in decay, through whoſe default it is ſo?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether the Church of your Pariſh be now vacant or deſtitute of an incumbent or no, and if it be, how long it hath béen ſo, and who is the Patron, and whether he ſuffereth the Benefice to lye vacant, and occupieth the glebe land, and taketh the tithes and other fruite to himſelfe during the time of the vacation, or who els occupieth and taketh the ſame, and by what authoritie?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether your Church be a Parſonage or Vicaredge, preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, a donatiue, or otherwiſe ſerued by a Cure? Whether did you euer heretofore heare or knowe that it was a Parſonage or Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redge, and how came it to be decayed from being a preſentatiue to be
<pb facs="tcp:25870:5"/>
in the ſtate it nowe is, and when was it firſt decayed from being a benefice preſentatiue as you remember?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether your Fonts or Baptiſteries be remoued from the place where they were wout to ſtand, or whether any perſons leauing the vſe of them: doe Chriſten or Baptize in Baſons, or other prophane veſſells, not cuſtomably vſed in the Church before time, or whether any Chriſten without eyther Godfather and Godmothers, and the ſigne of the Croſſe appoynted by the booke of common prayer?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Articles concerning Eccleſiaſticall officers.</head>
               <p>WHether the Chancellor, Archdeacon, Commiſſary, officiall, or any other, vſing Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction in this Dioces, their Regiſters or Actuaries, Apparitors or Sumners, haue at any time winked at and ſuffered any Adulterers, Fornicators, inceſts, or other faults or offences preſented vnto them, to paſſe and remayne vnpuniſhed and vncorrected for Money, Rewards, Bribes, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Frendſhip or any other partiall or affectionate reſpect?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether at the Archdeacons viſitations which haue bin ſithence 1586. the Archdeacon of your Archdeaconrie or his officers hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Church wardens for a Certificate from the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate of your Pariſh, thereby to vnderſtand whether the Iniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſaide Biſhop giuen in his viſitation held in that yeare 1586. haue bin duely and preciſely obſerued or not, according to the Tenor and effect of one of thoſe Iniunctions?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether any haue beene lawfullie preſented to the Chancelor, Archdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Commiſſarie, or Official, within theſe three yeres paſſed, for any crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall Courts: who neither haue made their purgation, for the infamie of the ſame offence, nor haue receaued pennance, whereby the pariſh hath béen ſatiſfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Articles concerning Schoolemaiſters.</head>
               <p>WHether the Schoolemaiſters within your pariſh openly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly, in any Noble or Gentlemans houſe, or in any other place be of good and ſincere Religion life and Conuerſation, and bée diligent in teaching and bringing vp of youth: and whether they haue bin examined allowed and licenſed for Schoolemaiſters, by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or his officer in that behalfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether your Schoolemaiſters doe themſelues receiue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion as often as they ought to doe, &amp; whether they bring with them ſo many of their Schollers as be of age ſufficient, and of
<pb facs="tcp:25870:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
capacity by inſtructions to receiue the Lordes Supper.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether your Schoolemayſters doe orderly on Sondaies with their Schollers come to the Church of their Pariſh where they teach, and there ſee their Schollers placed in ſome conuenient place, ſo as they doe not diſquiet the Miniſter or pariſh in time of deuine ſeruice: but may exerciſe themſelues godly in reading and hearing the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and Sermons, and in anſwering with the Congregation in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of publique prayers.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether the Schoolemaiſters eyther priuate or publique doe teache their Schollers the Catechiſme aucthoriſed by publique auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, at the leaſt once euery weeke: and doe inſtruct and examine them in the ſame, or doe teache any other Catechiſme: and what Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme is it that they ſo teach?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether any of your Schoolemaiſters be knowne or ſuſpected to reade vnto their Schollers priuately any bookes, or priuately to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in theyr yong yeares eyther in Poperie, Superſtition, or diſobedience, or contempte to her Maieſtie and her Lawes Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, by publique authoritie allowed?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether any Schoolemaiſters vnder pretence of Catechiſing their Schollers (which is a moſt godly order carefully by them to be obſerued) do keepe Lectures reading, or expoſitions in diuinitie, in their houſes, hauing continuall repayre vnto them of ſuch people as ſeeke after innouations, and refuſe their owne Pariſh Churches and their Miniſter?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Articles concerning the Pariſhioners and others of the Laity.</head>
               <p>Whether all Houſholders in your Pariſh, cauſe their Children, Seruants and Apprentices, both mankinde and womankinde, being aboue ſeauen yeares of age and vnder twenty, which haue not learned the Catechiſme, to come to the Church on Sondayes and holy-daies at the times appoynted for Catechiſing, &amp; there diligently and obediently to heare. And what be the names of thoſe that do not cauſe their Children, Seruants and Apprentiſes ſo to come to the Church to be inſtructed and examined.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether any doe worke, or kéepe any Shop, or any parte of their ſhop open vpon the Sabaoth dayes, or vpon any holy-daies appointed by the Lawes of the Realme to be kept holyday?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether you your ſelues or the Churchwardens in the yeares before you, haue ſuffered any vnmaried women being begotten with
<pb facs="tcp:25870:6"/>
Childe to goe out of the Pariſh before ſhe hath done pennance, or any man defamed of whoredom to departe vnpuniſhed vpon direction ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the ordinary, and forth of whoſe houſes haue they gone away with Childe vnpuniſhed, and how many vnmaried women which haue bin deliuered within your pariſh theſe three yeres laſt paſt haue gone away without doing of penance?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether there bee any in your Pariſh, that doe themſelues for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, or dehort others from comming to publique prayer and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word Preached, condemning all forme of praier which they cal ſtinted prayer, calling our Churches the Temples of Idols, and our Preachers falſe teachers ſent in the Lordes wrath: which leude opinions, ſome Sectaries haue lately broched?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether any man keepeth or readeth any ſeditious and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall bookes, or pamphlets written by any which enuaieth againſt the Religion now receaued, or the order and gouernement of the Church now publiquelie eſtabliſhed, or that ſtirreth vp the hearers to innouation, or altring of the Churches gouernement by Lawe now eſtabliſhed?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether the Pariſh Clarke be appointed according to the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient cuſtome of the Pariſh with the allowance of the ordinarie, and whether he be not obedient to the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate: and whether he be able to reade, and whether he keepe the bookes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the Church fayre and cleane, and cauſe the Churche and Quier, the Communion table and the fonte to bee kepte cleane and decent againſt the ſeruice time, the Communion, Sermon, and Baptiſme.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether there be any perſon or perſons Eccleſiaſtical or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall within your Pariſh, or elſewhere within this Dioces, that haue reteyned or kept in their cuſtodie, or that reade, ſell, vtter, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe, carrie, or deliuer to others any Engliſh bookes or Libels, ſet forth either on this ſide or beyond the Seas by Papiſtes, or others, againſt the Quéenes Supremacie in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, or againſt true Religion and Catholique doctrine, or the gouernment and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church of England now within this Realme, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and eſtabliſhed by common authoritie, and what their names and ſurnames are?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether there be any in your Pariſh which for any cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer forbeare to come to Church to publique praier, or to heare Gods word preached, pretending it vnlawfull to come to our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies as the Church of England now ſtandeth?</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb facs="tcp:25870:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>9 Whether any do refuſe to receiue the holy Communion at their owne Miniſters handes, either becauſe he is not a Preacher, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he duely obſerueth the order of miniſtration appoynted by the Booke, and who they be that do go from their own Pariſh to receiue at any other Miniſters hands?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether any of your Pariſhioners hauing a Preacher to their Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, do abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to any other place to learne or followe after ſuch innoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as are there taught.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Whether the people of your Pariſh, eſpecially houſeholders hauing no lawfull excuſe to bee abſent, do reſort with their children and ſeruants to their Pariſh Church or Chappell on the Holi-daies and on the Sondaies to morning and euening praier. And who they be that either negligently or wilfully abſent themſelues, or come ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie late to the Church vpon the Sondaies eſpecially, or that walke, talke, or otherwiſe vnreuerently behaue themſelues in the Church, or vſe any gaming or paſtime abroade, or in any houſe, or ſit in the ſtréete, or Church-yarde, or in any Tauerne or Alehouſe vpon the Sonday or other holi-day in the time of Common praier, or reading of the Homilies, either before or after noone?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether the forfeiture of twelue pence for euery time of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from Church (appoynted by a Statute made in the firſt yeare of the Quéenes Maieſties raigne) bée leuied and taken according to the ſame Statute by the Church-wardens of euery perſon that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth, and by them be put to the vſe of the poore of the Pariſh: if it be not ſo leuied, by whoſe default is it?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether there be any Inne-keepers, Alewiues, Victualers or Tiplers, that ſuffer or do admit any perſon or perſons in their houſes to eate or drinke, or play at Dice, Cardes, Tables, Boules, or ſuch like games in the time of Common praier or Sermon on the Sondaies or Holi-daies: or any Butchers or other that commonlie vſe to ſell meate or other thinges in the time of Common praier, Preachings, or reading of Homilies. And whether in any Fayres or common Markets, falling vpon the Sonday, there bee any ſhewing of any wares before Morning praier bee done? And whether any markets or ſelling of wares be vſed or ſuffered in any Church-yards on the Sabboth day by common Packmen or Pedlers going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether the Church-wardens of the laſt yeare haue giuen to the Pariſh a iuſt accompt of the Church goods and rents that were
<pb facs="tcp:25870:7"/>
committed to their charge, according vnto the cuſtome that hath bin aforetime vſed, and what Church goods they or any other haue ſold, and to whom, and whether to the profite of your Church or no, and what hath béen done with the money thereof comming?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether the Church-wardens and Sworne-men ſince the viſitation holden 1586. haue of any priuate corrupt affection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed any crime or other diſorder in their time done in your Pariſh, and haue not preſented the ſame to the Biſhop, Chauncellor, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſarie, or ſuch other as had authoritie to reforme the ſame: and whether they, or any of them at any ſuch time as they ſhould haue béen at deuine Seruice on Sondaies or Holi-daies, and ſhould there haue obſerued others that were abſent, haue béen away themſelues at home, or in ſome Tauerne or Alehouſe, or els about ſome worldly buſines, or at Boules, Cardes, Tables, Dice, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaming, without regarde of their office and duetie in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether your Miniſter and you the Church-wardens, or any other of your Pariſh haue on your reueſterie made any orders, or do vſe to call any parties before you for any cauſe to bee ordered by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes, and ſo do vſe a kind of preſbiterie, or cenſuring ouer your neighbours?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether any of your Pariſh being of conuenient age, haue not receiued the holie Communion thrice this laſt yeare at the leaſt, and namely at Eaſter laſt, or thereabouts for once, and what their names are, or which at their receiuing haue not ſignified the ſame before to your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, that he might conueniently examine them, and who haue refuſed to come to him to bee exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether there bee any in your Pariſh that adminiſter the goods of thoſe that bee dead without lawfull authoritie, or any that ſuppreſſe the laſt Will of the dead, or any Executors that haue not fulfilled their Teſtators will, eſpecially in paying of Legacies giuen to the Church, or to other good and godlie vſes, as to the releefe of pouertie, to Orphanes, poore Schollers, poore maydens marriages, high waies, Schooles, and ſuch like, and by whom are they ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether there be any in your Pariſh that hath or doth offend contrarie to the Statute made in the xxvii. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the viii. for the reformation of Vſurie, and reuiued by an Act made in the xiii. yeare of the raigne of the Quéenes Maieſtie
<pb facs="tcp:25870:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that now is, and what be the names of ſuch offenders?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Whether hath your Miniſter, or any of the Pariſh, not being Iuſtices of Peace, without the conſent or priuitie of the Ordinarie, cauſed any to do penaunce or be puniſhed, either openly or otherwiſe, for any crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes, and what bée the names of the parties, who haue béen ſo puniſhed, and in what manner?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether the Iniunction ſent from my L. Grace of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and the High Commiſſioners in Nouember 1587. directed to your Miniſter and Churchwardens not to receiue ſtrange preachers not licenſed, be obſerued: and whether the ſaid Iniunction remaine in your Church, or no?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Whether there be any among you that do vſe ſorcerie or witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafte, or that bee ſuſpected of the ſame: and whether anie vſe anie charmes, or vnlawfull praiers: and whether anie doo reſort to anie ſuch for helpe and counſell: and what be the names both of ſuch as vſe it, and of ſuch as reſort to them for helpe?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether anie couples that be maried in priuate houſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe thrée yéeres laſt, haue béen knowen or ſuſpected to haue béen married after anie other order, than is appointed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon that the one partie or the other are noted to bee ſuch as refuſe to come to the Church, or diſlike of the orders of the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether there be among you any Blaſphemers of the name of GOD, great or often Swearers, Adulterers, fornicatours, inceſtuous perſons, bawds or receiuers of naughtie and incontinent perſons, or harbourers of women with childe which be vnmaried, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueying or ſuffering them to goe away before they do anie penance, or make ſatiſfaction to the Congregation: or anie that be vehementlie ſuſpected of anie ſuch faults, or that be not of good name &amp; fame tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching anie ſuch crime and fault: anie dronkardes or ribaldes, or anie that be malicious, contentious, or vncharitable perſons, railers, ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or ſowers of diſcord betweene neighbors, and ſpeciallie railers againſt Miniſters, and againſt their marriage?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether there be anie in theſe parts that haue married within the degrees of affinitie or conſanguinitie, by the Lawes of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: or anie that being diuorced or ſeparated for the ſame, doo yet notwithſtanding inhabit and keepe companie ſtill together: or anie that being maried without thoſe degrees, haue vnlawfullie forſaken their wiues or huſbands, &amp; married others. Anie man that hath two
<pb facs="tcp:25870:8"/>
wiues, or anie woman that hath two huſbands: anie that beeing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorced or ſeparated aſunder haue married again: anie that haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or contracted themſelues without the conſent of their parents, tutors, or gouernors: anie that haue married without Banes thrice ſolemnlie aſked: anie couples maried that liue not together, but ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſlie liue apart.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether there be anie in your pariſh, who will come to heare the ſermon, but wil not come to the publique praier appointed by the booke of common praier, making a ſchiſme or diuiſion as it were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the vſe of our publique praier, and preaching.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether the Miniſter and Churchwardens haue ſuffered anie Lords of miſrule, or Summer Lords or Ladies, or anie diſguiſed perſons, or May games, or anie morrice dancers at anie times to come vnreuerentlie into the Church or Churchyard, and there to dance or play, eſpecially in the time of common praier: and what they be that commit ſuch diſorder: or that accompanied or mainteined them?</p>
               <p n="28">28 Whether there be among you anie notorious euill liuers, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuſpected of any notorious ſinne, fault, or crime, to the offence of Chriſtian people, or any that ſtubbornly refuſe to conforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to vnitie and godly Religion now eſtabliſhed by publique authority: or any that beareth abroad rumors of the alteration of the ſame, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe that diſturbeth good orders, and the quietneſſe of Chriſtes Church, and the Chriſtian Congregation?</p>
               <p n="29">29 Whether all ſuch admonitions and Iniunctions, as haue come to your pariſhes from my Lord of <hi>London</hi> in and ſithence the laſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation for the obſeruing of anie order for the Church, or putting downe anie diſorder, haue ben dulie kept euer ſince or no, &amp; by whoſe default they haue not been kept?</p>
               <p n="30">30 Whether there be any married women or others within your pariſh, which after child-birth doo refuſe or contemne to come to the Church to giue thanks for their deliuerie, &amp; to haue the prayers pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, appointed in that behalfe by the booke of common prayer.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Whether any carry out the Infants to be Chriſtened in other pariſhes, as miſliking the order of Chriſtening in their owne pariſh: whether any preach in any Noble mans or Gentlemans houſe, not being licenſed of the Biſhop?</p>
               <p n="32">32 Whether any within your Pariſhes doo reſort vnto barnes, fieldes, woods, out-houſes, or to any extraordinarie Expoſitions of Scriptures, or conferences together: and ſo doo (as it were) make a
<pb facs="tcp:25870:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſeuerall Church or Sect vnto themſelues; or be drawers or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of others to any ſuch ſchiſmaticall and damnable Sects.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Item, whether your Parſon, Vicar or Curate haue wittingly maried together any couples whereof the woman hath ben got with childe, or carnally knowen before mariage: or whether the man for money or reward hath married anie woman that hath committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie with another man, without publique acknowledgement of their offences, and reconciliation to the pariſh: &amp; what are the names of all ſuch that haue been ſo maried in anie ſuch caſe, and when, and by whom they were ſo maried together?</p>
               <p n="34">34 Whether any doo keepe their Children vnbaptiſed longer than the Sunday after Birth, vnleſſe it be for ſickneſſe of the childe, or other vrgent occaſion: &amp; whether any doo carrie their children from the Pariſh they are borne in, to other Pariſhes to bee baptiſed? And whether any do refuſe and carrie their children from their owne Pariſh to bee baptiſed in other places, or do bring ſtrange Miniſters into their owne houſes, to baptiſe their children priuatly according to their owne phantaſies?</p>
               <p n="35">35 Whether the order of praiers on Wedneſdaies and Fridaies, ſet forth lately by the moſt reuerend Father the Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie, by him appoynted to bee obſerued through his whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, be obſerued as it is required, and who bee they that vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of it do bring in any newe deuiſed order, prayer, or faſtes, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the preſcribed order of that booke?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="legal_notice">
            <p>The ſeconde bils which are to be deliuered at Michaelmas next, are to be brought into Maiſter Blackewels office in Iuie Lane, Regiſter to my Lord Biſhop of London, betwixt Michaelmas and the eyght day of October following, or els the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Side-men making default herein, are at their perils to ſhew cauſe the x. of October next in the Conſiſtorie in Pauls, why they ſhould not according to law, bee proceeded agaynſt for their contempt.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
